It makes it easier to cast
my real Visual Genjutsu on him
（イタチ）このまま少し　ループにかけて→
by keeping him trapped in
a small loop like this.
本来の視覚による幻術に
かけやすくする。
（サスケ）なら…。
So Kabuto's trapped in
your loop now?
カブトは　そのループってのに
ハマったってことか？
それが　イザナミ…。
And that's the Izanami?
いつ　仕掛けた？
When did you cast it?
The first time Kabuto stabbed me
with that blade.
（イタチ）カブトが最初に　俺を
その刀で突き刺したときだ。
あのときか…。
Back then, huh?
しかし　どうやって？
But how?
You mentioned a Visual Jutsu
that is possible without sight.
視覚に訴えることなく→
ハメる瞳術があると
言っていたが…。
視覚じゃない瞳術とは
どういうことだ？
How can Visual Jutsu work
without eyesight?
Izanami is a Visual Jutsu that
works with the physical senses
イザナミは　自分と相手…。
２人の体の感覚によって
ハメる瞳術だ。
of both yourself and your opponents.
２人の体の感覚？
The physical senses of two people?
行動の中の任意の一瞬…。
As you are battling your opponent,
you take a record, like a photograph,
その一瞬の
己と相手の体の感覚を→
of the physical senses that
both you and your opponent
一度　瞳術で
写真のように記憶する。
are feeling during that instant,
with your Visual Jutsu.
仮に　それをＡとする。
We'll call that A.
更に　時の流れの中で→
As time progresses,
you find "B" is a more
important moment,
より印象的な場面をＢ　Ｃと→
then you record "C" and
so on with Sharingan.
次々に写輪眼で記憶する。
一定の瞬間を記憶したら→
Then you recreate
those exact physical senses.
So you're using your powers to
create an exact copy of A.
前に記憶したＡと
同じ体の感覚を→
わざと　もう一度再現させた
Ａ´を作る。
We'll call this A'.
イザナミは　そのＡと　Ａ´を重ね→
FLOW OF TIME
By overlaying
and connecting A to A',
更には　Ｂ´
Ｃ´を再現することにより→
FLOW OF TIME
the Izanami also links
a path for B' and C'
FLOW OF TIME
to create fluctuations within
a fixed time.
一定の時間の中を　さまよわせる。
In other words, it's the power
to create an infinite loop.
つまり　無限ループを作る能力だ。
もちろん
失明することと引き換えにする。
Naturally, all in exchange for
one's own sight of course,
イザナギと同じにな。
exactly like Izanagi.
カブトの意識は
その幻のイタチと俺を相手に→
So Kabuto's consciousness
is trapped inside
fighting a phantom you and
a phantom me for all eternity.
ずっと無限に続くループの中で
閉じ込められるってわけか…。
いや…　この術には→
No.
There is an escape route built
into the jutsu.
そのループから抜け出る道が
用意されている。
そもそも　イザナミは→
The Izanami was developed
to admonish
イザナギの術者を戒め
救うために作られた術だからな。
and save an Izanagi user.
どういうことだ？
What does that mean?
You know a little about
the Izanagi already.
イザナギは　お前も少し
知っているようだが…。
あれは　運命を変える→
It's called the perfect
Uchiha Visual Jutsu
うちはの完璧な瞳術だと
いわれていたそうだ。
designed to change destiny.
己の結果に
うまくいかないことがあれば→
If something does not go
the way you want it to,
you can just erase that outcome
and start all over.
その結果をかき消し
もとに戻れる。
いわば　都合のいい結果だけを
選び取っていける仕組みだ。
Ultimately, you can pick
and choose
the most desirable end result.
これから語るのは
イザナギと対をなす→
What I'm about to tell you now
is the story
of the Uchiha's Izanami,
and how it came to be.
イザナミが誕生した
うちはの歴史の一部だ。
お前にも
知っておいてもらいたい。
I want you to know this too.
うちはの…。
The Uchiha's Izanami…
the story of its creation?
イザナミ誕生の歴史…。
Izanagi and Izanami
Long ago, there was
a great battle
過去の大きな戦いにおいて→
うちは一族が
決して失敗できぬとき→
that the Uchiha Clan could not
afford to lose.
The Izanagi tuned out
to be invaluable.
イザナギが
大きく貢献する術となった。
((ライ：いけっ！
Go!
（みんな）うわ～！
おのれ！　罠を仕掛けていたか！
Damn it! They had set a trap!
なにっ！？
What?!
殲滅せよ！
Die!
うちはに　イザナギあるかぎり→
As long as we have the Izanagi,
we can't lose!
(我らに敗北は　ありえぬのだ！
ハッハッハ！))
が　しかし
結果を己の思うがままに→
However…
There's a bigger risk than
just blindness
変えられる術には
失明以上の大きなリスクがあった。
to a jutsu that allows the casters
to choose their own ending.
その強力すぎる瞳力は
術者をおごらせ→
Most who used this overly
powerful Visual Jutsu
個を暴走させる
要因となってしまったらしい。
could not handle it and
abused their power.
それでも　イザナギを使う者が
１人なら問題ない。
It was fine,
as long as there was
only one user of the Izanagi.
However, when two or more used it,
だが　それが２人以上となると→
うちは一族内で　都合のいい結果の
奪い合いが始まった。
there was a scramble
within the Uchiha Clan
to see who could get the best result.
((バル：イザナギが使えるのは
お前だけではない！
You are not the only one
who can use Izanagi!
お前が　リーダー面をするのは
気にくわぬ！
I don't like you bossing us around!
だが　手柄を立てたのは事実。
But I'm the one who
accomplished it!
忍の世界は　結果がすべてよ！
In the shinobi world,
results count for everything!
ほほぅ　ならば　その結果を→
Well then…
I shall rewrite that result…
我が手柄として
書き換えてやろうか。
俺の　イザナギでな！
with my Izanagi!
口ほどにもない！
You're only talk.
俺が　うちはを…。
I shall rule the Uchiha…
no, the entire shinobi world…
いや　忍世界を
仕切ってみせるわ。
俺の　イザナギでな！
with my Izanagi!
その野望　俺が引き継ぐ。
I'll take over your wish…
この　俺のイザナギでな！
with my Izanagi!
ハハハハハハ！
（ナカ）ハハハハハハ！
(ハハハハハハ！))
このような
一族内での　イザナギによる→
What was created
in order to stop this inter-clan
rivalry over the Izanagi…
都合のいい結果の奪い合い。
それを止めるために
作られたのが→
is the Izanami.
イザナミだ。
Normal vision-based genjutsu
is powerless
視覚相手に　視覚では
幻術に　ハメられないからな。
against Visual Prowess…
((ナカ：お前も
俺に刃向かうというのなら→
If you intend to oppose me too,
I have no choice.
しかたがない。
（ナオリ）争い以外にも
解決策はあるはずよ。
There has to be a way to
settle this without fighting.
ハッ！　俺の手は
すでに血で染まっている。
My hands are already stained
with blood.
立ち止まることなど
許されるはずもない！
As if I'm going to stop!
（ナオリ）あなたは
自分をわかってない！
You don't know yourself!
自分自身の本当の力を
わかってないのよ。
You don't know your own true strength!
ええい　黙れ！
Oh, shut up!
今なら引き返せる。
It's not too late to
turn back right now!
その意志があるのならば
私の手を。
If you have the will,
take my hand!
フン！　騙されるか！
I won't be fooled!
どうしても
言うことが聞けないのなら→
If you still refuse to listen,
I'm prepared as well.
私にも覚悟がある。
この俺の背後をとるとは　やるな。
Sneaking up behind me, nice work!
だが　イザナギがあるかぎり
俺を倒すことはできん。
But as long as I have Izanagi,
you cannot beat me!
次で終わらせる！
It's over for you!
ハァ…　ハァ…　ハァ…。
バカな！
I don't believe this!
My right eye…
俺の右目は　イザナギとともに
視力を失ったはず！
I should have gone blind
with the Izanagi!
The Izanagi that you depend on so much
will not protect you.
（ナオリ）あなたの頼りとするイザナギは
あなたを守ってはくれない。
Shut up!
黙れ！
(くっ…　まだ　まだだ！))
N-Not… Not yet!
（イタチ）そもそも　現実とは
運命という名の偶然の産物だ。
In the first place,
reality is a product of chance
that we call fate.
我々には　予想がつかない。
We can't predict it.
だが　イザナギは
都合の悪い現実をねじ曲げ→
But Izanagi can twist around
an inconvenient reality
新たな運命を導く。
and lead it to a new fate.
本来の現実を
術者の都合だけで→
REALITY
At a whim,
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
the user can change
the original reality into a new one.
新たな
現実へと変えてしまう。
NEW REALITY
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
the user can change
the original reality into a new one.
敵からすれば
倒したはずの相手が→
NEW REALITY
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
To the enemy,
a fallen opponent will revive,
ANOTHER REALITY
IZANAGI ACTIVATED
To the enemy,
a fallen opponent will revive,
復活するのだから
たまったものではない。
so it's an intolerable jutsu.
そこで　イザナミは→
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
The Izanami is set up to take someone
who is using the Izanagi
イザナギで　己の結果を
都合のいいように→
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
to change the outcome
to benefit oneself,
変えようとすると
一生　同じところを→
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
and cause them to endlessly
circle around in a loop.
グルグルと　ループさせる。
イザナギが
究極の瞳術だと思っていたが…。
I believed that Izanagi was
the ultimate Visual Jutsu.
イザナミは　その上をゆく
瞳術ということか。
But that means the Izanami is
a far superior Visual Jutsu.
Izanami forms a loop
イザナギの現実を
ねじ曲げる体感が→
around the physical sensation
of Izanagi twisting reality.
イザナミのループを
呼ぶことになるとはな…。
だが　イザナミは
イザナギを止めるための術。
The Izanami is a jutsu meant
for stopping the Izanagi.
There's an escape route built
into the loop.
ちゃんと　そのループから
抜け出る道も作られていた。
これは　本来
うちはの仲間を→
Originally, it was a jutsu
to save Uchiha comrades
おごりと怠慢から
救うための術だった。
from arrogance and negligence.
術で簡単に
結果から逃げる者…。
It's to stop you from taking
the easy way out with jutsu.
それを止めるための術。
((ハァ　ハァ…。
なぜだ！
Why?!
イザナギで変えられない運命など
ないはずなのに！
There's no destiny that
Izanagi cannot change!
自分のしてきたこと→
Accept the things you've done,
そして　その先に待つ
未来を受け止めるのよ！
and take hold of the future
that awaits you!
血に染まったこの手は
許されるはずもないだろう。
There's no way I can be forgiven
for the blood on my hands.
それでも　受け止めて。
Still…
Take hold of it!
うお～っ！
もう　イザナギには頼らない。
I won't rely on Izanagi anymore.
(現実を受け止め　前に進む))
I'll accept reality
and move forward…
（イタチ）本来の
結果を受け入れ→
IZANAMI ACTIVATED
Once one accepts the original outcome
and stops trying to run from it,
逃げなくなったとき
おのずと→
REALITY
the loop will stop.
イザナミのループは解ける。
術に頼ることなく→
This jutsu guides you toward
accepting your fate,
運命を自分で
受け入れるように導く術。
instead of relying on jutsu
to change it.
抜け道のある術など
実戦では　危なくて使えない。
But a jutsu that has an escape
is too dangerous to use in actual combat.
そういう意味で
イザナミは　禁術になっている。
That's why Izanami is
a Forbidden Jutsu.
だからカブトが　自分以外の誰かに
成り代わることをやめれば→
If Kabuto stops trying
to transform himself,
ループから　出ることはできる。
he can stop the loop.
うちは一族　闘争の歴史。
The strife-filled history
of the Uchiha…
その歴史の中で
イザナギに伴う術者のおごり。
The arrogance and recklessness
of those who used Izanagi…
個の暴走…。
そして　一族内での対立。
and how they clashed and
were stopped by Izanami…
それを止めるためのイザナミ。
イザナギとイザナミが対の禁術として
存在する歴史はわかった。
I understand now
why both Izanagi and Izanami
came to be Forbidden Jutsu.
過去を教訓として
運命を受け入れ→
And I see how one must learn
from the past
前に進んでいくための戒め
というのも　わからなくはない。
and accept one's fate
and move on.
だが　なぜ…　なぜ　そんな術を
わざわざカブトにかけたんだ？
But…
But why bother casting this
on Kabuto?
脱出できるってことは…。
If there's a way to escape…
こいつは　昔の俺に似ていた。
He reminds me of the old me.
すべてを手に入れたつもりで→
He thinks by acquiring all there is,
何でもなせると猛進しようとする。
he can accomplish
whatever he wants.
だからこそ　己の失敗におびえ→
He makes himself
believe that he can't fail,
己に失敗はないのだと
自分に　ウソをつく。
and lies to himself.
結果　それを
ごまかす方法として→
I stopped listening to anyone else.
I stopped trusting anyone.
他人の力を
信用しなくなったのが俺だ。
カブトの場合は
それをごまかす方法として→
In Kabuto's case,
he is so deluded
他人の力をもすべて
自分の力だと思い込んだ。
that he thinks all these powers
are his and his alone.
こいつのこともわかるんだ。
I empathize with him.
この忍の世に翻弄された者同士→
We were both used by
the shinobi world…
どうしても自分自身を許し
認めることができないことも…。
He can neither forgive himself
nor accept himself for what he truly is.
確かに　こいつの
やっていることは間違っている。
What he is doing is certainly wrong.
だが　こいつだけを
責めるのも間違いだ。
But he's not completely to blame
for not being able to realize that.
カブトには　俺と違い
死ぬ前に気づいてほしい。
My chance has passed,
but he can still forgive himself
before he dies.
こんなやつのために→
Why would you ever feel
like you need to help him do that?
なんで　兄さんが
そこまでする義理がある！？
こいつと兄さんは違う！
He is not like you.
You were perfect!
兄さんは完璧だった。
（イタチ）サスケ。
Sasuke…
俺は　別天神という
瞳術まで使い→
I tried to control you
with the Visual Jutsu
お前を操るかたちで
導こうとした。
called Koto Amatsukami.
誰よりも　お前を子供扱いし→
I treated you like a child
守るべき対象としてしか見ず→
because I thought you
needed my protection.
お前の力を信用していなかった。
I didn't trust your strength.
なんであれ　一つとして
一つで完璧なんてものは→
It may be that
a perfect being does not
exist at all in the world.
ないのかもしれない。
だからこそ　補うものが
引き寄せられるように生まれ→
Sometimes two who seem
to be opposites
are actually two sides
of the same coin.
そばで対を成して→
They can only succeed when
they actually work together.
初めて少しでも
よい方向へ近づけるのだと思う。
イザナギとイザナミの術のように。
Like the Izanagi and Izanami.
俺を見て　俺になかったものを
お前には探してほしい。
Look at me,
and find in yourself what
I was unable to find in myself.
だから　俺を完璧だったなんて
言ってくれるな。
Do not say I was perfect.
まずは…。
First of all…
（カブト）そんなはずはない！
僕は完璧になる存在だ！
Impossible!
I will be a perfect being!
こんなのは…　僕じゃない！
This is…not me!
いつまで
大蛇丸に成り代わっている！
How long will you
imitate Orochimaru?
このループから抜けたいなら
お前の失敗を見つめ直せ。
If you want to exit this loop,
reexamine your mistakes!
うるさい！
Shut up!
《ここで火遁がくるのは
わかっている》
I know he's going to come at me
with a Fire Style Jutsu.
水遁　水龍…。
水遁　水龍弾の術！
Water Style…
Water Dragon…
Water Dragon Missile!
うわっ！
《写輪眼で　術の先読みを…》
He anticipated that jutsu
with Sharingan!
何が失敗だったというんだ！？
How did I get this wrong?
この僕のやってきた
どこに失敗があったと！？
Where did I…
make a mistake?
（カブト）僕は　ただ
自分の存在を誰かに→
All I ever wanted was someone…
to appreciate…
見てもらいたいだけだった！
who I was!
認めてもらいたいだけだった！
All I wanted was to
be acknowledged!
それのどこが
失敗だったというんだ！
Where is the mistake in that?!
まずは　ありのままの自分を→
First of all…
you had to accept yourself
as you were.
自分自身が
認めてやることだった。
そうしえさえすれば
誰にもウソをつくことはなかった。
Then you wouldn't have
had to lie to anyone.
お前にも　俺自身にも。
To you…or to me.
ウソに信頼はなく
背中を預ける仲間はできん。
If you lie to yourself,
how can you have friends?
How can you trust or
be trustworthy?
そして…　ウソは
本当の自分すら見えなくさせる。
Lies will keep you from
ever seeing your true self.
《こんな…　こんなとこに
閉じ込められなきゃ→
If I wasn't trapped here…
今頃　戦争に勝って…》
I'd have won this war by now.
とっくに寝てる時間だったのに。
I'd be sleeping by now.
イタチめ～！！
Damn you, Itachi!
（ウルシ）もう９時か…。
It's 9 o'clock already?
どうした？
いや→
Something wrong?
No…
さっさと　この戦争を終わらせて
ゆっくり寝たいと思ってな。
I just wish we could
wrap this up quickly
so I could get a good night's sleep.
俺たち　末端の忍には
もう何が何やら。
They never tell us lackeys
what's going on.
詳しいことは
いつも　わかんねえしよ。
まあな。
That's true.
お前　この戦争が終わったら
どうすんだ？
So, what are you gonna do
when this war is over?
とりあえず　家に帰るかな。
Well, I'll start by going home.
戦争が終わって　五大国が
このまま仲間でいるなら→
If the war ends and
the Five Great Nations
continue to be allies…
ずっと任務で会えてない　弟も→
then maybe my little brother who's been
on a mission for a long time,
帰ってきてるかも
しれないからさ。
can finally come home.
帰る所があるやつは
うらやましいな。
I envy those who have
a home to return to…
お前も来るか？　俺と一緒に。
え？
You want to come with me?
Huh?
俺の家は　孤児院だからよ。
My home is an orphanage.
それに　弟がいたら
傷をみてもらうといい。
And if my kid brother's back,
he can take a look at your wounds.
ありがとう　ウルシ。
I appreciate that, Urushi!
《今度こそ
帰ってくるといいな…。
I really hope
you come back this time…
カブト》
Kabuto.
これより　穢土転生の術を止める。
I'll stop the Reanimation Jutsu now.
（イタチ）これで…
転生の死人は　すべて消える。
And…all the reanimated dead
will fade away.
戦争も終わりの時が近づく。
That should end the war.
なら…　兄さん　あんたも…。
But…
you'll be gone too, Brother.
俺は
木ノ葉隠れの　うちはイタチとして→
I'll have protected my village as
もう一度
忍里を守ることができる。
Itachi Uchiha of the Leaf
once again.
もう　この世界に未練はない。
I have no more regrets.
なぜだ！　兄さんに→
Why?!
Why help the very village that
put you where you are now?
あんなことをさせた
木ノ葉のために→
なんで　また兄さんが！？
兄さんが許せても
俺が　木ノ葉を許せない！
この世に未練がないだと？
俺を　こんなふうにさせたのは
兄さんなんだぞ！
ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
((サスケは　お前に任せる。
俺は１人で何でもしようとし
失敗した。
(今度は
それこそ仲間に任せるさ))
お前を変えられるのは
もう俺じゃない。
だから　せめて…
この術を止めることが→
今の俺にできること。
ナルトに託したことを
ないがしろにしないためにもな。
（イタチ）穢土転生の術を止める。
印を教えろ。
月読！
（イタチ）約束は果たした。
あとは頼んだぞ。　ナルト。